Guide to the David C. Collins Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Chittenden Collins papers
1845-1851
MS 886
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The papers consist of family correspondence of which the largest group is made up of letters between David Collins and his wife, Clarissa. Also included are three letters to Collins from his daughters. The letters discuss domestic affairs such as the upbringing of children, health, and family relations.
Collins, David Chittenden, 1805-1861
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift in 1956 as part of the Daniel Collins Family Papers (MS 894).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This small collection consists of correspondence of David Chittenden Collins with family and a few others between the years 1845 and 1851. The bulk of the letters are thirty-three exchanged between Collins and his wife, Clarissa (Ely) Collins during his business trips to New York City, and three letters to Collins from his daughters. These letters deal almost entirely with household matters and family news; frequent topics are the upbringing of the children, the family's health, and relations with Clarissa Collins' family. The remaining nine letters from other correspondents discuss such matters as renting property and hiring servants.
The letters are arranged alphabetically by author. They were given to Yale University in 1956, and previously formed part of the Daniel Collins Family Papers, Manuscript Group Number 894.
Biographical / Historical
David Chittenden Collins was probably born in 1803, the son of Elizabeth Watkinson and Alexander Collins. After Alexander's unexpected death in 1815, Eliza moved with her children from Middletown to Hartford, Connecticut. In Hartford, David was employed at his Uncle David Wilkinson's hardware store. In the early 1820s, Collins began a blacksmith shop, where he forged and tempered axes. In 1826, Collins & Co. was formed as a partnership between David, his brother Samuel, and their cousin, William Wells. The company produced axes and was extremely successful. Collins died in 1861.
Families; Husband and wife; Canton (Conn.: Town); Manufacturers; Collins, Clarissa Ely, b. 1814; Collins, David Chittenden, 1805-1861
- Inventory
  - American Art Union, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Belden, Mary H., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Collins, Clarissa (Ely), 1845-1851, undated (Box 1, Folder 3 - 9)
  - Collins, David Chittenden, 1847-1848 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 12)
  - Collins, Edith, 1845, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - D____, M____, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Ely, Richard S.?], 1847 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Harrington, Mary K., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hewins, Mary K., undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Low, Annie, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sheffield, Joseph Earl, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Staples, Mrs. E., undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper clipping, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 21)